Welcome back to
a new week.
We will now start with an
introduction to UML (in particular static
modeling with UML)
and object orientation.
Before that, a few words about
UML as such, since, as I said,
this language will generally take
up more space in the lecture.
So UML (Unified Modeling
Language) is a standard modeling
language for
software engineering.
Quite common both in
the literature and in practice.
Possibly known from school, if
you had computer science classes
there and object-oriented
work was done.
You might also have at
least seen class diagrams in
your pre-college
computer science class.
That's this first kind of
diagram that's just shown up here.
This is probably more
of an object diagram, not
a class diagram, but this comes from
the same family of diagrams within UML.
As I said, it's based on object-oriented
concepts, which we'll talk about in a moment.
But there are also
various other types of diagrams
that are not directly related to object
orientation but are still part of UML.
So it's a
very comprehensive modeling
language, a framework with
different kinds of models.
It is also now over 20 years
old and has spread accordingly since then.
Usage you will certainly see (for
some of the types of diagrams
we're looking at
here) in other courses.
For Komedia students I'm not sure,
but for ISE and computer science students:
Advanced Programming Techniques, for
example, or in the
Software Engineering lecture, you will certainly
encounter some of the things again.
Both static and dynamic
modeling is supported by UML.
We also see here already
that graphs play a role.
There is less textual modeling
and also not necessarily very formal.
So the different types of
diagrams have different degrees of formality.
There are purely descriptive diagrams and
there are also somewhat more formalized diagrams.
Here is a summary of
what I have just said.
So there are mainly
visual-graphical means within UML.
There is also text, of course, but
there is less mathematical modeling in UML.
Both static and
dynamic modeling is supported.
In the lecture we will first
deal with static modeling in UML.
Later, however, there will be chapters
dealing with dynamic modeling within UML,
after we will have
covered Petri nets in between.
In
other respects:
We had seen so
different distinction types of models.
So besides "static" / "dynamic",
it was about "qualitative" or "quantitative".
This is both
covered in UML.
So for example, the class and
object diagrams that we're going to
look at first definitely contain
qualitative aspects and some quantitative aspects.
As I said, primarily UML is
used to specify software systems, especially
object-oriented
software systems.
With regard to the
transparency of the models,
so to speak, there are both
whitebox and blackbox models in UML.
So it depends on the type
of diagram you're looking at, whether
you think of it more
as a whitebox or a blackbox.
That's both
covered in principle.
In terms of the level
of formality, semi-formal at best.
So this is not mathematical
modeling and not very formal.
The syntax is
still somewhat formally defined.
So it's stated
somewhere what the
diagram forms are in the
first place, what legal diagrams are.
The semantics is usually
not very formally specified.
So what such a diagram means concretely, there
is an understanding of it, but that is not
necessarily mathematically elaborated in
somehow full logical, mathematical stringency.
And the use
in software development depends,
of course, on the process
model that you are dealing with.
I had also indicated that last week,
that in classical development processes, like the
waterfall model, models tend to
be created explicitly as well.
And then UML would definitely
be a tool of choice.
In other process
models, such as agile
development, models are not used
as much or as explicitly.
There, it will
not necessarily be the
case that a class diagram
is always created before development.
So we talk about software development "on a
large scale" when it comes to such structured
procedural processes, and then UML
would perhaps be even more present.
UML can
be used not
only for
visualization/specification of models.
There are also approaches that actually generate
code directly from models created with UML.
I had already
mentioned model-driven/model-driven development.
Then it would be the case that
UML diagrams are actually generated in a
tool, from which Java code is then generated,
for example (which usually still has to be
supplemented, but already provides
a framework for the implementation).
And then, of course, the role of
models would again be strengthened against other approaches.
Here is an overview, schematically,
of the various UML diagram types.
These are not
all that exist, either.
There are one or
two more diagram types.
UML is also
still under development.
But this is already a
fairly large snapshot here, and
some of the concepts here we're going
to bring to life in the lecture.
So we're not going
to kind of go
through all of the 10, 12,
14, or however many boxes this is.
But various of the
chart types we'll actually see.
We can look at.
What do we have here?
So on the one hand, we have
this distinction between structural and behavioral diagrams.
That pretty
much maps to:
This part is
just the static modeling.
And the part over here
is for dynamic modeling using UML.
So since we're doing static modeling first,
we're going to stay left here first.
And in particular, we're going to look
at just these two diagram types there: Class
diagrams and
Object diagrams.
We're not going to cover the other diagram
types that come up here in the lecture.
And then later,
after we've covered Petri
nets, we'll look at
dynamic modeling with UML.
That's where activity diagrams from
UML will appear, for one thing.
These are ultimately related
representatives of Petri nets.
Therefore it makes sense
to deal with them afterwards.
And then we'll deal in
particular with the UML state
diagrams, which are structured
means with much more expressiveness
than the flat state diagrams
that we looked at last week.
And, as I said, some of these types
of models would be more static or more dynamic.
The left/right distinction, so to
speak, is between static and dynamic.
But there are still the
distinctions qualitative/quantitative, black box/white box, etc.
And something of all of
them shows up here somewhere.
So there are charts here that
are more qualitative versus quantitative, etc.
We will then also
see (for those that
we look at specifically) how
that classifies in each case.
But in general, a lot of the types
of models we discussed earlier occur in UML.
First, as I said, class and object
diagrams, as just shown on the slide.
The two on the left from
the top representatives below structure diagrams.
What's being
statically modeled there?
Essentially, what's being
modeled is this.
It's about objects, things, their
properties, and relationships between them.
So those are the three
things that it's kind of about.
What are the things/objects that are in
the system that we want to talk about?
So, what
exists there?
And what properties do
the respective things have?
That can be different
properties for different areas,
which the appearing
things must have.
And what are the
relations between the things?
So, properties refer
to one thing.
Relationships are between different things
that can occur in the system.
The point then is to
record the state of the system.
How it
is composed.
So, not necessarily what concrete values must
be present at a point in time, but:
How is
the state organized.
What must be known
about the system in order
to capture what it looks like
at a particular point in time?
And
also:
How can
it evolve?
Whereby the "how" of development would
of course be rather dynamic modeling.
Here it is more about
what states are possible at all.
So
not:
How do you get
from one state to another?
But
rather:
Which states are
possible at all?
And that also limits
how the system can develop.
And docking to what
we did last week:
What operations
are offered?
So, what can
you do with things?
Without specifying what exactly comes
out when you do that.
But in
the first place:
What is the
interface, so to speak?
Which operations
are possible?
At first, this sounds
less exciting than modeling behavior.
Dynamic modeling is
always more demanding.
That's why we also
start with static modeling.
But, as we
saw in last week's
article, we can
start with static modeling.
What are the objects
involved in the first place.
So, how is the
data structured in the system?
Which operations are
possible, i.e. are offered?
This also limits
the dynamic behavior.
So having such a
precise static model at first
is also an important
aid later on during implementation.
This is especially relevant
for larger software systems.
And, this will not be in
the foreground in this lecture, but:
Such a static modeling also allows
the application of certain design principles.
So, especially if a lot
of modeling is done with
object orientation, then there are certain
principles what a good object-oriented design is.
And if you use
the UML language, then
these principles are very easy to apply,
so they are also easy to recognize.
So there are
certain programming techniques.
Inheritance, for example, you may
be familiar with if you
worked with Java
in school, for example.
And inheritance is quite
nice at first, but
on the other hand, it can also
be a trap to use that too much.
Just because it's there
in the programming language
doesn't mean you have
to use it everywhere.
And a clear design, a clear
modeling using UML, can make it easier
to first make sense of
when you should actually use inheritance.
Again, these are
patterns that are certainly
discussed, for example, in
the lecture "Advanced Programming Techniques".
So you can
then also ask:
What is a good
or a bad model?
If one commits oneself then
to a certain model language.
What is this
object orientation all about?
So, where do the
objects come into play?
First of all, this can be defined in a
very abstract way, just as we defined our concept
of models and systems in a
very abstract way at the beginning.
So, what is
the basic idea?
Somewhat simplified, the world consists of
objects that are related to each other.
That's first of all a statement
that you can make about the world.
And the
idea is:
Since computer science systems often have to do with
the world or are supposed to represent things from
the world, one transfers this basic
structuring of the world (or this
view) precisely to modeling and
to software development in general.
How then is it to
be put a little more precisely?
So the
idea is:
You take the data that should
somehow be present in the system.
These will later
be called attributes.
And these are
combined with the functionality.
This is called methods, and corresponds
to operations from the previous week.
And this data,
together with the functionality
that operates on this data, is
organized together, summarized together (this is
also called encapsulation), and assigned
to individual objects in each case.
So an object
summarizes: certain data
and methods/operation that
should operate on it.
And then each object is
able to receive method calls.
So to perform operations that
process the data or again
trigger other operations
on other objects.
The objects can, so to speak, exchange
data with each other via the methods/operations.
This is already
a contrast to
what we saw last week
for this vector graphics domain.
Because there it wasn't that the
Pictures, the images, themselves somehow offered methods.
But rather there
were these operations.
They were taking Pictures as input
and possibly returning Pictures as output.
So it
worked both ways:
You could take an image as
input and return an image, or
you could just generate an
image from some numerical data.
But it wasn't like the methods
were directly tied to the images.
We'll see that in
contrast again in a moment.
And
importantly:
The benefit of this kind of approach should
just be that these objects or whole types of
objects (whole classes of objects, as
we will say then) should be realized
once, and then be able
to be reused in different contexts.
It's not about describing an object somehow,
but about making it more general, so that
we can then reuse existing
models in different application contexts.
Let's actually look at this in a somewhat naive
illustrated way first, from a programmer's point of view.
Although this is
not a programming lecture.
But to understand this
basic idea of object orientation,
it is not wrong to have
a look at it with pseudo code.
And that's what we'll
do with the example domain
that we've just been
reminded of, vector graphics.
And let's imagine that we want to
describe a small picture that is somehow
built up step by
step from different operations.
So that's
what's here now.
We'll
imagine:
We first draw a
rectangle with certain dimensions.
That would be our
picture 1, Picture 1.
Then we color that red,
so we have another Picture.
So now a red
rectangle with these dimensions.
Then we
rotate it.
Get a new picture p3,
and move this picture p3 by
some x/y coordinates, and then
get our final picture p4.
That would be one way
we could describe such a step-by-step
construction of an image using
the operations from last week.
And then we could
paint p4 on the screen.
What's noticeable here, and may
seem clumsy at first glance:
We have these intermediate images here,
each of which has its own
name and then actually always has the role
of serving as input for the next image.
This passing on of these image
variables, so to speak, could be avoided.
Object-oriented programming tries
to avoid this by
leaving it somewhat
implicit, so to speak.
So instead of imagining that
you create a new image every
time you perform an
operation, you simply say:
You have an image and
you work on that directly.
So in an object-oriented way, you would say
here, the image is summarized with its operations.
So there is an image p, which is created
at the beginning once as a rectangle with these dimensions.
And the fact that this is
now written in capital letters is
rather due to the fact that this is already
somewhat based on a concrete programming language, namely Java.
Apart from that, there
is no significant difference.
Then you would create a new
image and then you would say that
you now color
this image red.
Now rotate this
image by angle 30.
Now move this image
to the following coordinates.
That is, in contrast to here
above one does not have several pictures,
which are built up gradually and then
also still separately from each other further exist.
So here above you would have p1, p2, p3,
p4, they all still exist, also the intermediate steps.
While here
one simply says:
On the one image
p perform these operations.
So you don't always have, as here
above, one image in and one image out.
But you work on one
image, which is automatically passed on.
On the one hand, this is
a bit shorter, you could say.
But of course
it also has disadvantages.
Because here it is so that this image
is overwritten, so to speak, in each case.
Whereas here above you really have
values for the individual images and
could quite well continue to
use p2 in addition to p4.
These are simply two different
approaches to working with operations.
And object orientation uses
just this second way.
This is probably not desirable
in every situation, but with
object orientation this is
the way to go.
Compare this
with arithmetic.
If you add numbers, the
old numbers do not disappear.
Yes, the situation up here is more
like how you work with arithmetic expressions.
You have
intermediate results.
But adding the numbers five and three does
not result in the five becoming the eight.
Instead, a new
number eight comes out.
And the five and
the three are still there.
Just
like here:
When I end up with the
red, twisted, shifted rectangle, it's not
that the original rectangle
has disappeared as a result.
Here below, however, the original rectangle
is overwritten with, then at the end,
the final rectangle with
color, rotation, and new position.
Where does
this come from?
What is the difference, so
to speak, between these two views?
For this, we had written
down our operations last week.
So there were explicit occurrences
of images as inputs and outputs.
So "color" took an image and
a color, and returned a new image.
And analogously with
the other operations.
Now, in object orientation, you
don't do that so explicitly.
But in the end, the picture,
so to speak the class of objects,
which is the main
issue here, is set implicitly.
So you create
a class called "Picture".
It might have a subclass
for the concrete, more specific things
that you have at the beginning, that you can
start from, i.e. the basic shapes rectangle, circle etc..
And then there are analogous
methods to the operations given here.
But they work implicitly
on one Picture object each.
So you just say,
within the class Picture
there are encapsulated operations
for coloring, rotating, moving.
And here Picture does not appear
again, neither as argument nor as result.
Because these methods are
encapsulated in the Picture class,
they always work
automatically on a picture.
So, when I call "color",
I do it on an image.
And the result, the colored picture,
is what comes out after the operation.
So the picture on which I
call the operation is changed by it.
I don't have to
explicitly return a new picture.
And we will find something
like that in our diagrams.
Not necessarily with exactly this syntax here,
for example not necessarily with this "void".
But this will be the nature of
our methods, not this more mathematical nature.
This is not
exactly Java syntax either.
There would be
some annotations missing,
probably some "abstract"
annotations for example.
But this is only
to illustrate the basic difference
between these
two approaches.
Does this mean that only operations
that always return an image are possible?
It looks
like this above.
That always makes: one image
as input, one image as output.
These are not necessarily all
operations that can be imagined.
So let's think about operations that are
not supposed to change an object, but
are simply supposed to
perform a calculation somehow.
So let's imagine that there
is another operation that simply determines
the dimension, the size, the diameter
or something like that for an image.
That would be from a mathematical
point of view, from an algebraic
point of view, simply
an operation "extent" for "extent".
It takes an image
and returns a number.
That would then be equivalent, if
encapsulated in the Picture class, to an
operation that just returns
a float value here.
So then there
are no arguments.
You don't have to
pass the picture as an
argument, because the method is
encapsulated in the Picture class anyway.
So you don't have to say from
which picture you want to have the dimensions.
This is always the current picture
on which you call the method.
It doesn't change the image,
but it returns an integer.
Then, if we write it this
way, we would have an operation
that takes no argument except the
Picture, which is implicitly given anyway.
But it does
have a return value.
Where on the previous slide it
said "void" everywhere, because you don't really
want to return anything, you just
want to manipulate the current picture.
And as I said, already the syntax in UML
is a little bit different than just shown here.
The syntax shown here
is based on Java.
In UML, which should not be
specific for a concrete programming language,
the syntax
is somewhat different.
So, for example, this specification for the
coloring operation would then look like this, and
not so programming-language
based on Java.
But that's just
a syntactical difference.
You have to
be a bit careful
when you specify diagrams that you
really stick to the UML notation.
Why do you
do object orientation?
Where is it
used in practice?
Well, I
already mentioned that:
One claimed advantage
is just reusability.
So by managing data and functionality
together, and by having concepts for modifying
behavior (keyword "inheritance", which I also
mentioned before, which we will look at
in more detail from
a modeling point of view),
it will be possible
to reuse functionality once developed
in different systems,
in different implementations.
Simply because the organization /
encapsulation of data and functionality
together lends itself well to transfers
to other application domains, even downstream.
Another important point is
compatibility with concurrency and parallelism.
These are concepts I hadn't mentioned yet,
which we'll look at in more detail, especially
in the
Petri net chapter.
So what we expect from software
today, we also expect from hardware, that
things don't just happen in a purely
linear way, but things also work in parallel.
So multitasking in
an operating system, for
example: object orientation is
well suited to represent this.
Because we have the encapsulated objects,
each of which has its own control
flow, its
own work.
And in different objects, this
processing of the control flow can,
in principle, take
place in parallel.
And the message exchange,
the ability to call
methods between objects, provides
a good structuring means for
communication in such a
multitasking or concurrent environment.
That's why, among other things,
people like to use that.
And, of course,
the original motivation:
Since the real world can often be imagined
this way (as consisting of things and their
properties, plus relationships between them), it's
just useful for many domains to directly
do software modeling
this way as well.
So, this is not the only
way, but definitely a prominent one.
Again, a very
naive example, just to
put this last
point a bit stronger.
So yes, here would be a real
world thing like that: a ticket machine.
You can also see that this
is probably not the most recent one.
So the image has been in the slides
of this lecture for quite some time, even with
my predecessor who gave the lecture last,
up until four years ago or so.
So a ticket vending machine, of
course it has data to store:
Destinations, zoning, travel
cost tables, etc.
That would
be the data.
And it has to
offer some kind of operations.
You can press buttons,
display prices, insert coins.
There is a cash
register that is managed.
There are tickets
to be ejected.
The idea
is just that:
The ticket vending
machine is an object.
It encapsulates certain data
and operations that are offered.
That would be such an
object of the real world,
which one would like to reproduce then
evenly by object-oriented modeling also in UML.
Two terms will
then appear as concepts:
Object.
I have already
mentioned object several times.
And then there is
the principle of the class.
This is simply
a type of object,
that is, the grouping
of objects with similar properties.
We will then also
look at class design.
That's
not mandatory.
There are also programming languages that
are object-oriented and do not contain classes.
There each object is
considered only individually for itself.
But the standard languages, such as
Java, also have a class concept.
An example would be the
class of all such automata.
There this would
be summarized generally: which
kind of data they must administer and which
functionalities are to be offered in each case.
That would be the class of the
ticket vending machines of this transport association.
Maybe there is also a more
general class of all ticket vending machines
at all, from which
this class then inherits properties.
The class will simply
group similar things together.
And then there are objects, which
are simply manifestations/instances of a class.
So the specific ticket vending machine
that was photographed on the pre-foil.
That would be an object
that belongs to this class.
And at other stations, or other
entrances to the Duisburg station, there
are other objects, but they all
have certain property types in common
and therefore belong to the
class of VRR ticket vending machines.
They then store other
information about the zoning
or about their own zone
etc. at other specific locations.